Hello Namaskar Jai Hind Vande Mataram.  You are watching
Jio News and we have brought for you
quick big news of selected importance from the country, world and your state and city.  But
before that, if you have not subscribed to our channel, then
subscribe to the channel and turn on the bell notification
and like and share this video as much as possible.
Before watching the big news,
today's question for you is which is the national aquatic
animal of India?  Option A Tortoise, Option B
Crocodile, Option C Ganges River Dolphin and
Option D Shark.  Answer this question by
commenting and tell us which state and city's
news do you want to see more?
Tell us by commenting so that we
can show more news of your state or city.  Let us now see
today's quick big news.
NCERT book controversy: Supreme Court
changes 2-month old order.  Those who
wrote the chapter on corruption in judiciary will not be removed.
Said the Centre and the State should decide.   The
Supreme Court has reversed its decision given two months ago on the controversy over the chapter on corruption in judiciary in the NCERT book.  On
March 11, the Supreme
Court had ordered that the three
academics who wrote the controversial part should be
removed and not given work again.
Now on Friday,
on the petition of the three educationists, the court
changed its order and said that the Centre, State,
University and institutions receiving government funds should
decide on this matter themselves.
Shubhendu Adhikari said that illegal Bangladeshis will be
handed over directly to BSF.  There will be
no court appearance.  Illegal immigrants do
not have the right to citizenship under CAA.  The West Bengal
government will hand over illegal Bangladeshi immigrants
directly to the Border Security Force (BSF) instead of the court.
This information has been given by West
Bengal Chief Minister Subhendu Adhikari.  The
new rule has come into effect from May 20
and Shubhendu said that instructions have been issued
to the Police Commissioner and the Railway Protection Force (RPF) in this regard.
According to the new rule, those who are found to be illegal immigrants will
not be eligible to get citizenship under the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA).
Supreme Court said if parents are IAS then
why reservation for children?  If the children of the creamy layer keep
taking reservations, they will never be able to get out of it.  The
Supreme Court
expressed concern over creamy layer candidates getting reservation in government jobs.  The court
said that if both the parents are IAS officers
then why should their children get reservation
?  Along with education and economic empowerment
comes social mobility and in
such a situation, if reservation is again demanded for affluent children, then
we will never be able to get out of this cycle.  The
bench of Justice BV Nagarathna and Justice Ujjal Bhuya made
this comment while
hearing a petition filed against a decision of the Karnataka High Court.
NEET paper was sold in five states.
Maharashtra has the highest
number of parents buying the CBI papers, followed by Rajasthan.
CBI
investigation has revealed that NEET paper was
sold in five states and the highest
sales were in Maharashtra and
Rajasthan was second.  The agency official
said that this information has come to light after interrogating the accused arrested so far
and scanning their digital gadgets.
CBI says
that after the arrest of more accused, the
paper leak case may turn out to be bigger.  For
this reason, the agency is not
able to determine how many students had purchased the paper.
Investigation has revealed that some family members had
further sold the paper to other people.
Elections for 26 Rajya Sabha seats will be held on June 18.  Retirement of 24 MPs including Kharge and Digvijay
in June-July.
By-elections are also being held on two seats.  Elections will be held on June 18 for 26 Rajya Sabha seats in 12 states.  The
Election Commission has declared him ineligible.   The
retiring members include Congress
national president Mallikarjun Kharge,
senior leader Digvijay Singh, former PM
HD Deve Gowda and 24 MPs.   The
current members in all these seats are
retiring between June 21 and July 19.
Apart from this, by-elections will also be held on two vacant seats.
These seats fell vacant after the resignation of Nationalist Congress Party (
NCP) national president and
Maharashtra Deputy Chief Minister Sunetra
Pawar and All India Anna Dravida
Munnetra Kazhagam (AIADMK) leader CV
Shanmugam.
Kolkata High Court said that cow
sacrifice is not necessary on Bakrid.  Refusal to ban animal slaughter notices in Bengal.
Humayun Kabir said I will
sacrifice.  The Kolkata High Court has refused to ban the
West Bengal government's guidelines on animal slaughter ahead of Bakrid.  The
court said that
cow, buffalo, bull or
calf cannot be slaughtered without the necessary fitness certificate.  A bench of Chief
Justice Sujay Paul and Justice Partha Sarathi
said that
slaughter of any animal in open public places is completely banned and
citing an earlier Supreme Court judgment, the court said that cow sacrifice on Eid-ul-Zuha is
not an essential part of Islam.
Parents approach Supreme Court against CBSE's three language policy.
Opposition to its implementation in ninth class.  The
bench of Justice Joy Malia Bagchi will hear the case.   A
group of 19 people has challenged the CBSE's three language policy in the Supreme Court.
Which includes students,
parents and teachers.  This petition has been
filed in protest against the implementation of three language policy in class IX.  The
Supreme Court will hear the case against this next week.  On
May 15, CBSE had
issued a circular to implement the three language policy from the academic session 2026.
Its notification will come into effect from July 1
and students have been given time till May 31 to choose the third language.
Smart
border security system will be implemented on Pakistan Bangladesh border.  Drone
radar smart cameras will be installed.  Shah said that
every illegal infiltrator will be thrown out of the country.
Union Home Minister Amit Shah
said that the Central Government will decongest about 6000 km of land bordering
Pakistan and Bangladesh within the next one year.  Will
implement smart border security system on the long border.
Under this, border surveillance will be strengthened using drones, radars, smart cameras and other
modern technology so
that infiltration and
smuggling can be completely stopped.
Addressing the BSF's Rusat Maji Memorial Lecture and BSF Invest Teacher Ceremony in Delhi, Shah said the
government has a zero tolerance policy towards illegal infiltration.
He said that
every illegal intruder present in the country will be identified
and sent back.   For
700 years, there was no namaz, only puja was performed in Bhojshala.
Muslim community tied black bands and
shops remained closed.  2000 policemen deployed in Dhar.
After nearly 700 years, only puja (worship) was performed in the Bhojshala premises in Dhar, Madhya Pradesh, instead of namaz.
Bhoj Utsav Samiti
installed the idol of Goddess Vagdevi on Friday and organised
darshan and puja.  A large crowd had gathered in the temple since morning
and the
family members of the workers were
also honoured at the Vagdevi temple.  The Indore bench of the Madhya Pradesh High Court had
declared Bhojshala a temple on May 15.  The Muslim community
offered prayers wearing black bands in protest against the decision.  They also kept their shops closed.
Around 2000 policemen were deployed for this security
and
strict monitoring was also being done on social media.   The person who
fed Jhalamdi to the PM is
receiving threats from Pakistan and Bangladesh.
Said in the video call that the shop will be blown up with a bomb.
Show your weapons as well.
Vikram Kumar, a Jhalamdi seller in Jhargram, West Bengal, is
receiving death threats.
Prime Minister
Narendra Modi had
bought and eaten Jhalmuri from Vikram's shop during the West Bengal election campaign.
Vikram Kumar came into limelight after this incident.
Vikram told that he was
getting phone calls from Pakistan and Bangladesh.  The
callers are threatening to blow up his shop.
Vikram told that
in a video call some people were also showing him weapons.
Due to this, he and his family are under a
lot of stress.
Actress Tisha's husband had come to surrender in the custody of Jabalpur Police.
Delhi AIIMS team will conduct second postmortem of the dead body.
CBI investigation gets approval.
Jabalpur Police has taken into custody Samarth Singh, the husband of actress-model Tisha Sharma, who is accused in the case.
He had come to
surrender in the district court on Friday evening.  Samarth has been
kept in the lawyers' cabin.
Anurag Srivastava, the lawyer representing Twisha's father Navnidhi Sharma, said the supporter was
wearing a mask inside Court No. 32,
which is the courtroom of the District and Sessions Judge.
He raised the question as to
under what authority he was
allowed to sit in that room.
Delhi riots accused Umar gets 3 days
bail.  Permission to go to hospital only for mother's treatment.  He has been
in jail for 7 years.   The
Delhi High Court has granted interim bail for three days to
Umar Khalid, an accused in the Delhi riots conspiracy case who has been in jail for seven years.   The
bail will be effective from 7:00 am on June 1 to 5:00 pm on June 3.
For this, Khalid will have to deposit a personal bond of ₹1 lakh.  The
High Court said that Umar had already
got interim bail for family functions.  He had complied with the court's
conditions and is
one of the main conspirators in this case.
But considering his mother's medical condition, a
sympathetic approach was adopted.
All the 22 hottest cities in the world are from
India, including 13 cities in Uttar Pradesh, and
hot winds blew even at night in 35 cities.  There is
no hope of relief from heat in the country for the next 3 days.
According to a QI Weather report, the
mercury was recorded above 47 degrees Celsius in 22 of the world's hottest cities at 3:00 pm on Friday.
All these cities are
from India and out of these 13 cities are from Uttar Pradesh.
Bolangir in Odisha and
Sasaram in Bihar were the hottest places.
According to the Indian Meteorological Department,
night temperature was recorded above 30°C in 35 cities of the country on Thursday.
Due to heat in Patna and Gaya in Bihar,
schools up to class 5 were closed from 22 to 26 May.
Meanwhile, three people lost their lives due to lightning in Madhepura and Saharsa on Thursday.   The
Punjab government has changed the timings of government offices and schools
and now the offices and schools will
open at 7:30 am and close at 1:30 pm.
Cockroach Janata Party founder said that Education
Minister Dharmendra Pradhan should resign.
Abhijeet's parents said that he had
not slept for two nights.  There is a fear that the son might get arrested.
Cockroach Janata Party founder Abhijeet
Deepak on Friday launched
his first online petition, seven days after creating the social media page,
demanding the resignation of Education Minister Dharmendra Pradhan in the NEET paper leak case.  Deepak
posted an expert video.  He said
that today we are going to start a petition
demanding the resignation of the Education Minister.
All of you should sign this petition as much as possible
so that questions can be raised on the mistakes of the system.
Abhijeet has formed the Cockroach Janata
Party
in protest against the remarks of CJI Suryakant who had called
some unemployed people cockroaches during the hearing on May 15.
Yogi said that if daughters are teased then Yamraj will
cancel the ticket.  The mafia goons
ran away after being buried in the mud.  Projects worth Rs 655 crore started in Deoria.
CM Yogi
fiercely attacked the Samajwadi Party in Deoria.
He said that these people
hindered development and exploited the public.  They used to
give benefits of schemes by looking at the face.  He used to
feed his family.  There was looting going on.   There
is nothing like that today.  The mafia was reduced to dust.  The
goons fled and those who
tried to show them the power of the public.
He himself went to the house of Yamraj.   The
second installment of Mahila Rojgar Yojana will be
released this month.  Minister Shravan Kumar
made the announcement.  You will get ₹100 in five installments.
Rural Development Minister of Bihar Government,
Shravan Kumar said that the state government is
continuously working to connect women with employment.  He said that under the
leadership of Chief Minister Nitish Kumar,
Bihar became the first state in the country where
such a scheme has been started for women.
He said that the women were not cheated
but were
given assistance of ₹10,000 to start self-employment and many
women have also started employment with this.
Shravan Kumar said that the process of
providing assistance of more than ₹2 lakh to women
is underway and there will not be much waiting for this.  The
next
amount will also be released this month.   The
decision on IRCTC scam case will come on June 9.  Lalu Rabri has challenged the decision of the lower court.
ED has filed the
charge sheet.  The hearing
in the money laundering case related to the IRCTC scam has been
postponed in Delhi's Rourkela Venue Court.
Now the court will give its decision on June 9.
In this case, the Enforcement Directorate (ED) has taken action against many accused including former Railway Minister
Lalu Prasad Yadav, Rabit Devi and Tejashwi
Yadav
and the
last hearing took place 6 months ago.  But the
court did not give its verdict that day.  The court has
already completed the entire process of framing charges
and now everyone's eyes are
fixed on the upcoming decision.
Digital education started in government schools through QR code.  The
entire syllabus will be open in front of the children as soon as they scan.  Katni became the
first district of Madhya Pradesh.  Katni district has set an example for the entire Madhya Pradesh in
improving the quality of education in government schools
and promoting technology-based learning.
District Institute of Education and Training (
DIET), Katni has developed a
QR code based
digital study system for students from class 6 to 8.
Katni has become the first district in Madhya Pradesh to implement this unique technological innovation.   The
main objective of this initiative is to ensure
100% utilization of resources available in government schools.  Along
with this,
uniform high quality and simple
study material is to be made available to students from rural and general background.  Under this, the
smart boards which have been gathering dust in schools for a long time are now going to
become the strongest medium of education for the students.   When
petrol and diesel became costlier by ₹4,
household expenses increased by ₹1000.  Gold,
milk, food and LPG are all expensive in Bihar.  Let us tell you that
inflation is going to increase further due to the Iran crisis.  Inflation has increased due to rising prices of petrol and diesel
and the value of rupee reaching its lowest level ever
at 96.83 per dollar.
Its effect has reached the food plate also.
On an average, the expenditure on every family has
increased by about ₹1000 per month.  At the same time, prices of rice,
pulses, milk and even oil have
increased.  Due to increase in diesel prices, freight charges have
increased and this is
likely to lead to further increase in prices in the coming days.  Today's
good thought: It is not right to be too straightforward
because straight trees are cut first
and the crooked ones survive.  Do let us know how you liked
this video in the comment section.  If you
like the video then please
like and share the video and to watch such interesting
[music]
videos subscribe to our channel Jio
News and press the bell icon
and do check
our playlist and
community tab to watch our old and latest videos.  So see you
[music] in the next video.
Thank you for now.